<!-- vi set expandtab -->
<section id="ssetup"><title>Installation</title>
 <section><title>Tarfile extraction</title>
  <para>If the package was downloaded as a tarfile, it should have
   the extension of <filename>tar.bz2</filename> or
   <filename>tar.gz</filename>.  For either case, <command>cd</command>
   into the directory in which you will install the directory tree and
   issue the command
  </para>
  <para> for the <filename>tar.bz2</filename> extension </para>
  <screen># tar -xjf &lt;path&gt;/.tar.bz2</screen>
  <para>OR, for the <filename>tar.gz</filename> extension.</para>
  <screen># tar -xzf &lt;path&gt;/os9disasm.tar.gz</screen>
  <para>In either case, a directory named
    <filename>cocodis<emphasis>x.x</emphasis></filename> will be created in
    the current location, and all files will be created under that directory.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section><title>CVS os9tools download</title>
  <para>If you have the CVS download of the <filename>os9tools</filename>
    hierarchy, you already have the necessary files in the
    <filename>os9disasm</filename> directory under
    <filename>os9tools/</filename>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section><title>Building and Installing the Package</title>
   <para>The packages now comes configured with <command>autotools</command>.
     This means that the configure process should be able to detect the
     operating system under which the process is running and set some compile
     parameters to suit your situation.  This should make it easier for the
     programs to be compiled under differing systems.
   </para>
   <section><title>Running the <command>configure</command> script</title>
     <para>The first thing you need to do after cd'ing into the top level
       of the distributions directory is to issue the command
       <command>./configure</command>.  This will inspect the system under
       which it is running and create various files, and especially the
       <command>Makefiles</command> that will handle the actual building
       of the system.
     </para>
     <note><title>Don't mess with the configuration files!</title>
       <para>Unless you know what you're doing and see that something in
         the configure setup needs to be fixed, please heed the following.
       </para>
       <para>There are a few files that you should never touch unless you
         have the autotools package.  If the timestamp of any of these
         are not as they should be, a complete reconfigure may be required.
         If you do not have the autotools utilities, you cannot do this, and
         even if you do, if it's version is not at least that of the one which
         originally built the configure scripts, then a complete reconfigure
         might be required.
       </para>
       <para><command>
         <itemizedlist>
           <title>The files that should not be touched are as follows:</title>
           <listitem>Makefile.am</listitem>
           <listitem>Makefile.in</listitem>
           <listitem>configure.ac</listitem>
           <listitem>configure.in</listitem>
           <listitem>aclocal.m4</listitem>
         </itemizedlist></command>
       </para>
       <para>If you do find that the system is trying to do a reconfigure and
         you are stuck, you can always remove your install of the package and
         re-extract it from the original tarfile.
       </para>
     </note>
     <section>
       <title>Options passed to <computeroutput>configure</computeroutput></title>
       <para>You can review the options accepted by <command>configure</command>
         by issuing the command <command>./configure --help</command>.  Most
         are the standard options that all <command>configure</command> scripts
         accept, but there are a few specific to this build.
       </para>
       <variablelist>
         <varlistentry>
           <term><command>--with-g09dis</command></term>
           <listitem>
             <para>&g09dis; by default is not compiled with
               &odis;.  The reason for this is that &g09dis; requires the &gtk;
               package to build and run.  In order to compile &g09dis;,
               <command>pkg-config</command> must be installed on the system.
               Since some systems might not have this, the configure process
               does not include <command>g09dis</command> in the compilation.
               If this option is not included, the Makefile for &g09dis; will
               be made, but will not be correct, and the
               <command>g09dis</command> directory will not be processed when
               the <command>make</command> command is issued.
             </para>
           </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
       </variablelist>
     </section>
   </section>
   <section id="buildprogs"><title>Building the program(s)</title>
     <para>After running <command>configure</command> you are now ready to
       build your program(s).  You build the programs by issuing the command
       <command>make</command>.  This will build your program, but won't
       install it.
     </para>
     <note>
       <para>You are not required to build from the top-level directory.
         The system is designed such that you can <command>cd</command>
         into any subdirectory and run <command>make</command> on just
         that directory.  It will, of course, recurse into any
         subdirectories below that level, but won't bother anything in a
         sibling or higher directory outside that particular level.
       </para>
       <para>This holds true for any of the <command>make
         </command> commands.  The command will apply over only
         that directory and any directories below it.  No higher directory
         or any outside this directory will be involved.
       </para>
       <para>In addition, you can also issue the command
         <command>make &lt;component&gt;</command> to build a single
         aspect of the suite.
       </para>
     </note>
   </section>
   <section><title>Packages needed to build the programs</title>
     <para>On a Linux system, most packages needed to build &odis; will
       likely already be installed.  If not, with most distros, they will
       be readily available.  If any needed packages are not installed,
       it should be seen when <command>configure</command> is run.
     </para>
     <section><title>Packages needed by G09dis</title>
       <para>To build and run <command>g09dis</command>, several packages
         are needed.  Even if running a precompiled package, several &gtk;
         runtime packages will be needed.
       </para>
       <para>In addition to the runtime packages, the corresponding -dev
         packages will be required to build the system.  Some of the packages
         needed are:
         <simplelist>
           <member><command>gtk+</command></member>
           <member><command>glib</command></member>
           <member><command>pango</command> (possibly)</member>
         </simplelist>
       </para>
       <para>In addition, to compile, <command>pkgconfig</command> is
         essential.
       </para>
       <para>Note that these package names will be accompanied with a version
         number, also.  &gtk; and <command>glib</command> should be version 2
         or greater.  Also remember that each of the above runtime packages
         (except for <command>pkgconfig</command>) will have a "-dev"
         counterpart that will be needed for compiling ( but not for running).
       </para>
     </section>
   </section>
   <section><title>Building and/or running on Windows</title>
     <para>These packages can be built and run on Windows systems.  The
       first requirement, and this applies to both &odis; and &gtk;,
       is the linux interface by which you can compile the programs.  I
       recommend MinGW, available from sourceforge.net.  There is another
       interface, called Cygwin, but it must be present to run the
       programs, but, as I understand it, programs compiled under MinGW
       can be run on a Windows system where MinGW is not installed.
     </para>
     <para>The &gtk; interface is available for Windows, and &odis;, of
       course, can be run from the command line without &gtk; if you do
       not wish to bother with &gtk;.
     </para>
     <para>The &gtk; interface is available by several means.  There are
       at least two executable install systems available (cannot recall
       the sources at the present), or the various modules can be
       installed piece by piece.
     </para>
     <para>
       In my opinion, the piece-by-piece installation is better in that,
       if one particular package is upgraded, you can simply overwrite
       the existing package and not have to do a complete reinstall.
       Tor Lillqvist maintains a pretty good and web page for this,
       accessible through either the gtk.org or the gimp.org website,
       following the links for Windows packages.  These are zip files,
       and you can begin by installing only the ones you think you will
       need, and, if you need something else, go back and install it in
       addition.
     </para>
   </section>
   <section><title>Installing the program(s)</title>
     <para>To install the program, you can issue the command <command>make
       install</command> (at any directory level you choose).  This can be done
       whether the program has already been built or not.  If it hasn't been
       built, issuing this command will cause anything that would need to be
       done before installing to be done before attempting to do the install.
       By default, this will install the &odis; binary in the directory
       <filename>/usr/local/bin/</filename>.
     </para>
     <para>Note that on most systems, to install to a standard location, such
       as <emphasis>/usr/local/bin/</emphasis>, you need superuser priviledges.
     </para>
     <section><title>Installing in an alternate location</title>
       <para>
         If you wish to install it elsewhere, then you can either simply copy
         the binary files to whatever destination you want after running the
         command <command>make</command>, or, if you wish to install the
         program(s) at a different location using <command>make
         install</command>, then you can include the option
         <command>--prefix=&lt;alternate-location&gt; </command> when you run
         <command>configure</command>.
       </para>
     </section>
     <section id="installwhere">
       <title>Install the binaries where the system can find them</title>
       <para>It may be very advisable to carefully contemplate the location
         where you will install the binaries.  This is especially true for
         &odis; if you are planning on calling it from within <computeroutput>
         g09dis</computeroutput>.  If you disassemble a binary from the menu
         in <computeroutput>g09dis</computeroutput>, a shell will be issued
         which will call up &odis; to do the work.  The call will be of the
         form <programlisting>"os9disasm program &lt;etc&gt;"</programlisting>
       </para>
       <para>It would be a bit difficult - and harsh - to hardcode a specific
         location into the program whereby everyone would be required to
         install &odis; at some specific location.  There are just too many
         differences between the various systems and people have preferences
         as to their install locations.  Therefore the call is called up in
         somthing of an open manner, and it's left up to the operating system
         to find &odis;.  The following gives some insight in how this can
         be assured.
       </para>
       <formalpara><title>Linux and Unix-type systems</title>
         <para>
           To find the directories searched in locating an executable program,
           from the shell prompt, issue the command
           <programlisting>echo $PATH</programlisting>  This will give a list
           of directories, separated by a colon, searched when looking for a
           command.  They are searched in the order in which they appear.
           <note>For security reasons, be aware that most Linux/Unix systems
             don't include the current working directory in the search path.
           </note>
         </para>
       </formalpara>
       <formalpara><title>Windows Command prompts</title>
         <para>If you're running from a POSIX shell, (msys, cygwin, or
           sh/bash/etc from an MS window, you can view the search PATH
           with the command as above,
           <programlisting>echo $PATH</programlisting>
           or, if from the MS command,
           <programlisting>echo %PATH%</programlisting>
           In msys/cygwin, you can add more search directories by editing
           one of the configure files.  Please see the documentation for the
           system for details.
         </para>
         <para>To alter the windows PATH, you will need to edit the
           <command>autoexec.bat</command> file.  To do this, you can
           either add your new directory to an existing PATH statement or add
           a line such as
           <programlisting>set PATH=%PATH%;your-new-directory</programlisting>
           Note that on most systems in Windows, the current working directory
           is normally included in the search path.  Therefore, you should
           be able to call &odis; successfully if &odis; is in the directory
           you are in <emphasis>when you call &odis;</emphasis>.  In other
           words, if the command
           <programlisting>ls os9disasm</programlisting>
           or
           <programlisting>dir os9disasm</programlisting>
           if you are at a DOS prompt
         </para>
         <para>succeeds, then you should be OK if you call <command>g09dis
           </command> as long as you don't <command>cd</command> somewhere
           else before doing so.
           <note><para>You can alter the PATH variable at any time by by
             issuing the above command in an MS window, but this change
             will be lost when the window is shut down and won't be in effect
             when starting a new window, or won't be available to the global
             Windows system.</para>
           </note>
         </para>
       </formalpara>
       <formalpara><title>Running g09dis from the Explorer Window</title>
         <para>I'm not entirely familiar with how this will work.  If you
           do this, probably the safest route would be to make certain
           that &odis; is in a directory listed in PATH.
         </para>
       </formalpara>  
     </section>
   </section>
   <section><title>The Documentation files</title>
     <para>Due to all the differences in systems, it has been decided at
       this time to not do an install of the documentation with a
       <command>make install</command> command from a higher directory.
       <!--       In fact, at this time, nothing is done with the documentation by
       makes from a higher level.-->  The html files are already built and are
       located in the <command>doc/html</command> directory.  These can be
       manually copied to any location you desire.  In addition, the xml source
       is available in the <command>doc</command> directory, and fresh html
       documentation can be created by issuing the command
       <command>make</command> in the <command>doc</command> directory itself.
     </para>
     <formalpara><title>Building your own documentation</title>
       <para>Since the source is available in the <command>doc</command>
         directory, you have the option of building the documentation in any
         format you desire.  Just run any docbook compiler on
         <command>os9disasm.xml</command> and create any output you wish.  The
         file <command>os9disasm.xml</command> will include all the rest of
         the files.
       </para>
     </formalpara>
   </section>
   <section><title>Installing the Standard Label Files</title>
    <para>In the top level directory, there is a directory named <filename>
      defs</filename>.  In this directory, you will find several files ending
      in "lbl".  These are the <command>standard label files</command>.
    </para>
    <para>Copy all these files into whatever directory you wish your DEFS files
      to reside.  The default is <filename>/dd/defs</filename>.  wish your
      "defs" directory to reside.  <filename>/dd/defs</filename> is the default
      location, but you can specify any path with the <command>-d</command>
      command-line option.
    </para>
    <formalpara id="dd-dir"><title>Getting /dd on a unix-style system</title>
      There are a couple of ways to get <filename>/dd</filename> to exist on
      a unix-style system.  The first is simply to create a directory named
      <filename>dd</filename> in the root directory and place all the files
      there.  However, I preferred to have my coco files in my
      <filename>$HOME</filename> directory.  This way, I did not have to worry
      about getting root permissions to modify files in this directory, so I
      created a <filename>coco</filename> directory there and created a
      symbolic link to that directory in the root directory.
    </formalpara>
    <para>On Windows, if you operate under MinGW, the simplest way is to
      create a directory <filename>/dd</filename> in the root directory.  Note
      that symbolic links are not available under Windows.
    </para>
    <para>In addition to these options, there is an option in &odis;
      <filename>-d</filename> which allows you to specify an alternate
      directory where the defs files are found.  This can be embedded in
      your <filename>command</filename> file for each disassembly you are
      doing.
    </para>
  </section>
 </section>
</section>
