<section id="quickref"><title>A quick reference of &odis; Operation</title>
  <simpara>In this section, we'll try to give a quick and brief rundown of
    the operation of &odis;
  </simpara>
  <section><title>Using the command file</title>
    <para>A <emphasis>command file</emphasis> (specified by the
      <computeroutput>"-c"</computeroutput> option) is practically mandatory
      for useful disassembly.  The <emphasis>command file</emphasis> is
      explained in more detail in <xref linkend="thecmdfile"/>.  Briefly,
      the <emphasis>command file</emphasis> can be used for three things.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Specify commandline options to pass to &odis;.</title>During
          the process of disassembling a program, you will undoubtedly have to
          run the disassembly several times.  To avoid the necessity of having
          to pass the options to &odis; each time, the commanline options (see
          <xref linkend="cmdoptions"/> for a desctiption of the options) by
          beginning the line with <command>"+"</command>.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara><title>Specify Data boundaries</title>You can specify
          sections of code as being data instead of code.  This cause &odis;
          to not attempt to disassemble these areas as code, but rather as
          either ASCII data, or constants.  These constants can be specified
          as either numeric data, either hexadecimal or decimal, or as
          labels.  This is explained further in <xref linkend="databounds"/>.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara><title>Specify an alternate label class</title>
          You can specify that the label reference for a line or range of
          lines is different than the default.  This is a rather complex
          concept and is explained more fully in <xref linkend="laddrmod"/>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara><title>Specify Comments to insert into source code</title>
          You can specify comments to be placed into the source listing and
          source file.  Comments can be beneficial to you during disassembly
          and also for later reference.  As you come up with comments, you
          can add them as needed.  See <xref linkend="asmcomments"/> for
          details.
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section><title>Data (noncode) Areas</title>
    <para>Some sections of the module will not be code.  There may be strings
      of text, or constants, which may be lookup tables or or other constants
      of any sort.  To specify a <emphasis>Data area</emphasis>, the command
      is preceded by a letter corresponding to the type of data.  Please
      see <xref linkend="dataaddr"/> for a fuller explanation.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section><title>Addressing Mode Specification</title>
    <note>
      <para>For a full description of <emphasis>Label Class</emphasis> please
        refer to <xref linkend="lblclass"/>
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>When disassembling code, &odis; will determine a reference in
      the operand to be a certain type based upon the <emphasis>mode</emphasis>
      of the assembler command.  &odis; has a default label class to assign
      a certain addressing mode, depending upon the target system.  For
      code in a program module, for example, &odis; will assume that, since
      register <emphasis>U</emphasis> usually points to the base of the
      data area, that something indexed by <emphasis>U</emphasis> refers
      to data, and will assign it class <emphasis>"D"</emphasis> (the default
      class for <command>D</command>ata).
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
